 <refentry id="kadeluser">
    
    <refmeta>
      <refentrytitle>kadeluser</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    
    <refnamediv>
      <refname>kadeluser</refname>
      <refpurpose>revokes user granted rights on given nodes and partitions (root command)</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>


  <refsect1>
    <title>SYNOPSIS</title>
    <para>
      <command>kadeluser [-l|--login login] [-m|--machine hostname] [-p|--partition partition]</command>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      kadeluser revokes deployment rights to the specified user on the given partition
    </para>

  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>OPTIONS</title>
    <para>
      <command>-l, --login</command> login
      the login of the user. This option can be used more than once to specify several users. 
    </para>

    <para>
      <command>-m, --machine</command> hostname
      specifies a host. This option can be used more than once to specify several hosts. By default, the deployment rights are revoked for all the nodes.
    </para>

    <para>
      <command>-p, --partition</command> partition
      the target partition. This option can be used more than once to specify several partitions. By default, the deployment rights are revoked for all the partitions.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>RETURN VALUE</title>
    <para>
      kadeluser returns 0 if it fails. Otherwise, it returns 1.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>EXAMPLE</title>
    
    <para>
      <command>kadeluser -l titi -p hda3</command>                       # revokes rights to user titi on all nodes on partition hda3
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>kadeluser -m node1 -p hdb6</command>                      # revokes rights to all the users on node1 partition hdb6
      </para>
    <para>
      <command>kadeluser -l toto -m node1 -m node2 -p hda1</command>     # revokes rights to user toto on node1 and node2 partition hda1
    </para>
    etc.

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <command>kaadduser, kadeluser, kaconsole, kacreateenv, kaaddnode, kadelnode, kadeploy, kareboot</command>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>COPYRIGHTS</title>
    <para>
      Copyright 2004 Laboratoire Id-Imag (http://www-id.imag.fr). This software is licensed under the GNU Library General Public License. There is NO warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  </refentry>
